ALICE GIAMPINO

Postdoctoral researcher

PERSONAL INFORMATION

Email: alice.giampino@unimib.it

PROFILE

I am a Postdoctoral Researcher in Statistics at the Department of Economics, Management and Statistics, at the University of Milano-Bicocca, Italy.

RESEARCH INTEREST

I am focused in Bayesian Analysis, in particular Bayesian Nonparametrics. Studying innovative perspectives in model-based clustering. Focus of my Ph.D. studies is related to Bayesian clustering methods with high dimensional data and multivariate time series with changepoint detection. I also worked on topic modelling techniques with distributions defined on the simplex.

Key-words: Bayesian methods, clustering, Dirichlet process.

EDUCATION

POSTDOC Dec 2023 -

University of Milano-Bicocca

PHD STATISTICS Nov 2019 - Nov 2023

University of Milano-Bicocca

· PhD in Statistics;

Specialised in Statistics and Mathematics

Visiting researcher at University of California, Irvine, US (May 2022 - May 2023).

STATISTICAL SCIENCE Oct 2017 - Sept 2019

University of Milano-Bicocca

· LM-82 Master's degree in Statistical science;

Specialised in *Statistics and Data science*; Date of achievement: 19 September 2019

Final grade: 110 summa cum laude (Top grade)

STATISTICAL SCIENCE Oct 2014 - Sep 2017

University of Milano-Bicocca

L-41 Bachelor's Degree in Statistics; Date of achievement: 12 July 2017

Final grade: 110 summa cum laude (Top grade)

LICEO SCIENTIFICO Sep 2009 - Jun 2014

IIS Carlo Alberto Dalla Chiesa, Sesto Calende (VA)

· High school leaving qualification in scientific studies;

Date of achievement: July 2014

Final grade: 96/100

WORK AND TEACHING EXPERIENCE

University of Milano-Bicocca, Milan (Italy) Lecturer - "Experimental Design", Department of Economics (35h)	Feb 2024 - Sep 2024
University of Bergamo, Bergamo (Italy) Teaching Assistant - "Statistics", Department of Engineering (22h)	Sep 2023 - Dec 2023
University of Milano-Bicocca, Milan (Italy) Tutor - "Statistical Model", Bachelor in Statistics (20h)	Feb 2022 - Apr 2022
University of Milano-Bicocca, Milan (Italy) PLS project (Scientific Degrees Plan) with high school lessons	Jan 2022 - Apr 2022
University of Milano-Bicocca, Milan (Italy) Tutor - "R for the multivariate statistical analysis", Bachelor in Statistics (20)	Oct 2021 - Jan 2022
TRUSTICERT S.r.l. Consultancy for statistical analyses.	Jun 2021 - Jul 2022
Politecnico di Milano, Milan (Italy) Teacher assistant, "Bayesian Learning and Monte Carlo Methods", Departme	Feb 2021 - Jul 2021 ent of Mathematics (20h)
University of Milano-Bicocca, Milan (Italy) PLS project (Scientific Degrees Plan) with high school lessons	Feb 2021 - May 2021
Politecnico di Milano, Milan (Italy) Teacher assistant, "Bayesian Learning and Monte Carlo Methods", Departme	Feb 2020 - Jul 2020 ent of Mathematics (20h)
University of Milano-Bicocca, Milan (Italy) PLS project (Scientific Degrees Plan) with high school lessons	Jan 2020 - Jul 2020
University of Milano-Bicocca, Milan (Italy) Investigate the presence of gender equality within the University	Apr 2019 - Jun 2019
University of Milano-Bicocca, Milan (Italy) Tutor - "Statistical Model", Bachelor in Statistics (20h)	Feb 2019 - Apr 2019
University of Milano-Bicocca, Milan (Italy) PLS project (Scientific Degrees Plan) with high school lessons	Dec 2018 - Apr 2019
Reply S.p.A, Milan (Italy) The Data Incubator - Data Science Bootcamp	2 May 2018 - 13 Jul 2018
University of Milano-Bicocca, Milan (Italy) Tutor - "Statistical Model", Bachelor in Statistics (20h)	Feb 2018 - Apr 2018

Currently research projects

1. _, B. Nipoti, A. Canale, "A Bayesian Method for Co-clustering Multivariate Ordinal Data with Informative Censoring", (2024+)

Target journal: Statistics and Computing;

2. _, M. Guindani, B. Nipoti, M. Vannucci, "Changepoint Detection with Random Partition Models", (2024+)

Target journal: Bayesian Analysis;

3. R.Ascari, _, S. Migliorati, "An extension of latent Dirichlet allocation", (2024+) Target journal: Journal of Machine Learning Research.

PhD courses projects

Master degree projects

- 1. Gradient R package;
- 2. Post selection inference fMRI Data;
- 3. Forest Fire Bayesian Analysis.

- 1. Outlier detection (R);
- 2. Ames House Price prediction (R);
- 3. Fraud detection (Knime, R).

CONFERENCES - WORKSHOP

Computational and Methodological Statistics (CMStatistics)

Dec 2023

Berlin, German.

Invited talk: "Changepoint detection with random partiton models"

Workshop - Approximation Methods in Bayesian Analysis

June 2023

CIRM, Marseille, France.

Talk and poster: "A Bayesian Method for Co-clustering Multivariate Ordinal Data with Informative Censoring"

ASMDA (Applied Stochastic Models and Data Analysis)

June 2023

Heraklion, Crete, Greece.

Talk: "A flexible generalization of the Latent Dirichlet distribution"

OBayes (Objective Bayes Methodology Conference)

Sept 2022

Santa Cruz, CA, U.S.

Poster session: "A Bayesian Method for Co-clustering Multivariate Ordinal Data with Informative Censoring"

COMPSTAT (Computational Statistics)

Aug 2022

Bologna, Italy.

Talk: "LEFDA: An extension of the classical Latent Dirichlet Allocation"

ISBA (International Society for Bayesian Analysis)

June 2022

Montreal, Canada.

Poster session: "A Bayesian Method for Co-clustering Multivariate Ordinal Data with Informative Censoring"

AWARDS

Ph.D. Fellowship

Nov 2019 - Oct 2023

University of Milano - Bicocca, Milan (Italy)

OBayes (Objective Bayes Methodology Conference) Sept 2022

Travel award

ISBA (International Society for Bayesian Analysis)

June 2022

Travel award

SUS5 (Stats Under the Stars 5th edition)

June 2019

Winner of the statistical hackathon in 2019.

PUBLICATIONS & PROCEEDINGS

Computational and Methodological Statistics (CMStatistics)

Dec 2023

Giampino A., Guindani M., Nipoti B. & Vannucci M. "Changepoint detection with random partition models"

Book of Abstract

ISBN 978-9925-7812-7-0

Classification and Data Analysis (CLADAG)

Sept 2023

Ascari R. & Giampino A., "A Flexible Topic Model" Book of Abstract ISBN 9788891935632

Computational and Methodological Statistics (CMStatistics)

Dec 2022

Ascari R. & Giampino A., "A generalization of the latent Dirichlet allocation" Book of Abstract
ISBN 978-9925-7812-6-3

Computational Statistics (COMPSTAT)

Aug 2022

Giampino A., Ascari R. & Migliorati S., "LEFDA: An extension of the classical LDA" Book of Abstract ISBN 978-90-73592-40-7

PERSONAL DATA AUTHORIZATION

Personal data can be used following the currently Privacy Laws.